Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is tzadi
hey צ"ה tzadi hey and we pick up at the bottom of
tzadi daled amud bet צ"ד עמוד ב', tzadi daled amud bet, we
have wrapping up today the issue about the story about the blood
of the chatas חטאת chatas and the laundering and then we're going
to transition over to the other aspects of the chatas חטאת chatas
in this perek פרק perek which we'll see will expand beyond the
chatas חטאת, chatas, but we've already mentioned when you cook it and
in an earthenware vessel, when you cook it in a metal vessel
and so on. So let's take a look at our Mishna משנה.
Mishna. Beget sheyatza chutz lekla'im venichnas בגד שיצא חוץ לקלעים ונכנס, Beget
sheyatza chutz lekla'im venichnas, so basically you have a garment that had
the blood of a chatas חטאת chatas and we just learned in
the previous mishnah משנה mishnah that you have to lekabbes bimkom kadosh
לכבס במקום קדוש, lekabbes bimkom kadosh, you have to launder it in
the Azara עזרה. Azara. So what happens if it gets the blood
of a chatas חטאת chatas and then it leaves the Azara עזרה?
Azara? So okay, bring it back and launder it. Okay, so nichnas
umekabbeso bimkom kadosh נכנס ומכבסו במקום קדוש, nichnas umekabbeso bimkom kadosh, so
bring it back and do the laundering in the holy place, that's
what you have to do. That's pretty straightforward. Nitma chutz lekla'im נטמא
חוץ לקלעים, Nitma chutz lekla'im, now let's say outside of the Azarah
עזרה Azarah this beget בגד beget that had the blood of a
chatas חטאת chatas became tamei טמא. tamei. Now you've got a problem
because you're not allowed to bring a tamei טמא tamei object into
the Azara עזרה. Azara. So what are you going to do? You
have on the one hand a mitzvah מצווה mitzvah to bring it
in to launder it and on the other hand a restriction of
bringing a tamei טמא tamei object into the Azara עזרה. Azara.
So you are going to magically make it not tamei טמא. tamei.
Here's what you're going to do: koro'o קורעו, koro'o, you tear the
garment so you make it a no longer a garment and the
tuma טומאה tuma goes away, and then machnis מכניס machnis or nichnas
נכנס, nichnas, probably should be machnis מכניס, machnis, I wonder what the
girsa גירסא girsa changes it to? No, venichnaso ונכנסו, venichnaso, okay, and
or I know mine's umachniso ומכניסו, umachniso, but anyway, then anyway you
tear it, you bring it in, umekabbeso bimkom kadosh ומכבסו במקום קדוש
umekabbeso bimkom kadosh and then you do because once you've torn it,
it stops being a beget בגד. beget. So which, by the way,
the obvious question is though, but if it stops being a beget
בגד, beget, are you laundering the beget בגד beget in a holy
place or you're just laundering now a piece of cloth, you know,
because we learned before, right, it has to be something that's ra'ui
lekabbel tuma ראוי לקבל טומאה. ra'ui lekabbel tuma. If the blood hits
a tiny little piece of cloth that's not considered a garment, or
we don't need technically a garment, we've abstracted garment to be something
that can be mekabbel tuma מקבל טומאה, mekabbel tuma, but anyway, if
it's not even something that can be mekabbel tuma מקבל טומאה mekabbel
tuma you don't have to launder it, right? If it hit the
blood when it was just a little piece of cloth. So that's
going to be the question the Gemara גמרא Gemara asks. The other
question which I'm asking, which I don't
know, would it be the same if it was like let's say
the bigdei kehuna בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna and then you know, then
it becomes tamei טמא, tamei, would it be the same thing? Then
you have to rip up the bigdei kehuna בגדי כהונה? bigdei kehuna?
Well, that's the other question I'm going to ask, why don't you
just put it in a mikveh מקווה? mikveh? That's what I said.
Yeah, I don't know, and the Gemara גמרא Gemara doesn't even discuss
that. Maybe because the putting of the mikveh מקווה mikveh would be
a type of a
laundering that would, you know, immerse it in water and then therefore
that would already be a type of a laundering, I don't know.
It doesn't mention putting it in the mikveh מקווה. mikveh. Now the
next case you're going to see you can't put in a mikveh
מקווה, mikveh, but anyway, okay. Kli cheres sheyatza chutz lekla'im venichnas veshovro
bimkom kadosh כלי חרס שיצא חוץ לקלעים ונכנס ושוברו במקום קדוש, Kli
cheres sheyatza chutz lekla'im venichnas veshovro bimkom kadosh, now let's say, see
we haven't even discussed yet the halacha הלכה halacha that if you
cook something, I mean we've mentioned it in passing, we haven't focused
on developing the halacha הלכה, halacha, that if you cook the chatas
חטאת chatas or we'll see other kodashim קודשים, kodashim, if it's in
a pottery vessel it says you shatter it, and if it's in
a metal vessel it says you scald it and rinse it and
so on. So the same halacha הלכה halacha though we taught in
the previous Mishna משנה Mishna which is that this shattering occurs in
a holy place. So let's say you went ahead and you cooked
it in this holy vessel and then you brought it outside the
Azara עזרה, Azara, so nichnas veshovro bimkom kadosh נכנס ושוברו במקום קדוש,
nichnas veshovro bimkom kadosh, bring it back in and do it as
is the required procedure.
Nitma chutz lekla'im נטמא חוץ לקלעים, Nitma chutz lekla'im, but let's say
this pottery vessel outside of the Azara עזרה Azara became tamei טמא.
tamei. You're not allowed to bring something tamei טמא tamei in, so
what are you supposed to do? And now, yes, so same idea,
but here of course here you understand why it didn't mention a
mikveh מקווה mikveh because you can't put a pottery vessel in a
mikveh מקווה, mikveh, it won't work. So here nokvo נוקבו, nokvo, make
a hole in it to make it stop being halachically a vessel,
so therefore but and it loses its tuma טומאה, tuma, but hasn't
completely shattered it, okay, venichnas veshovro bimkom kadosh ונכנס ושוברו במקום קדוש
venichnas veshovro bimkom kadosh and then bring it in. All right, Kli
nechoshet כלי נחושת, Kli nechoshet, similarly if you've got a copper vessel,
same idea, there you're supposed to do this merika ushtifa מריקה ושטיפה,
merika ushtifa, this scalding and rinsing, sheyatza chutz lekla'im nichnas umerko veshotfo
bimkom kadosh שיצא חוץ לקלעים נכנס ומורקו ושוטפו במקום קדוש, sheyatza chutz
lekla'im nichnas umerko veshotfo bimkom kadosh, it was brought out and bring
it back in and do the procedure. Nitma chutz lekla'im נטמא חוץ
לקלעים, Nitma chutz lekla'im, if it became tamei טמא tamei outside and
you can't bring it in as a tamei טמא tamei thing, pocho'o
venichnas umerko veshotfo bimkom kadosh פוחתו ונכנס ומורקו ושוטפו במקום קדוש. pocho'o
venichnas umerko veshotfo bimkom kadosh. You similarly you basically make a hole
in it or something like this, you crack it, okay, and it
loses its tuma טומאה, tuma, it's no longer a vessel, then you
bring it in and do it. You can't use it either. Well,
right, so we're going to see all of that, but anyway, but
what is funny to me is that this case also, why not
just put it in a mikveh מקווה? mikveh? You know, by the
garment maybe because they say putting in a mikveh מקווה mikveh would
already be like laundering it, but I don't understand why you don't
put this thing in a mikveh מקווה. mikveh. So I don't really
get what the point is about why that's not an option. Anyway,
I haven't seen a discussion about this, but I don't know if
your footnotes mention it or whatever. Anyway, there's a huge Tosafot תוספות
Tosafot here just to let you know, one of the reasons our
daf דף daf is going to be so short is because Tosafot
תוספות Tosafot tries wants to understand why like making a hole in
it or tearing it suffices. Because elsewhere we have this very strange
idea that if, let's say, my garment becomes טמא tamei, מת *tamei
met*, it touches a dead body, and then I tear it so
it stops being a garment. So then the הלכה halakha *halacha* is,
okay, it stops being טמא tamei. מת *tamei met*, but then it...
so it's not the garment itself that touched it, but then it's
like... but then why isn't it like it touched something that was
טמא tamei, מת *tamei met* because it touched itself? There's this very
weird idea that something is sort of seen like it touches itself,
so that even when it loses one status, it sort of gets
the next level, derivative status, because it touched itself. Anyway, it's a
very long תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafos*, that's not our issue, but I just
wanted to make you aware, one of the things that really makes
our next דף *daf* very small is this very large discussion. Yes.
So we said, you said that you put boiling water. I'm just
wondering because here says מרוק ושטפה במים *meruk ushtafah bamayim* says, at
least the way they translate here, scouring.
Scouring, in my mind, means you can like use a scouring pad.
Do you have to actually...
We'll see, let's wait till the next משנה mishnah. *mishnah*, okay? We'll
get to it, okay?
A notation here, so this is what you had
thought to... One cannot simply immerse the garment in a מקוה mikvah
*mikvah* outside the courtyard to purify it of its טומאה tuma *tumah*
since this might remove some of the blood and constitute laundering the
garment outside the courtyard.
Okay, that works, so who says that?
It says see חק נתן *Chok Nassan*, שפת אמת *Sefas Emes*.
Okay, some אחרונים *acharonim* say it. Fine, so that answers the garment,
does it... doesn't answer the metal one. Right. All right, you'll tell
me if there's a footnote about the copper one. Okay. All right,
anyway.
It says here to the best... can't be immersed in a מקוה
mikvah. *mikvah* since immersion might wash away some of the blood and
constitute a partial rinsing.
Ah, to the degree that the מריקה *merikah* and שטיפה *shtifah* is
also about physical stuff on the outside and not just... חזון איש
*Chazon Ish*. חזון איש *Chazon Ish*. All right, so there you go,
so we anticipated the answer. It's very funny that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* doesn't ask that question. All right, anyway, let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. מתקיף לה רבינא Ravina *Matkif lah Ravina*.
So רבינא *Ravina* challenged this משנה Mishnah. *mishnah*. קראו *Kera'o*, בגד beged
אמר רחמנא ולאו בגד beged. הוא *beged amar rachmana velav beged hu*.
What do you mean tear it? Once you tear it, it stops
being a garment. So it's very nice the טומאה tuma *tumah* went
away and you could bring it in, but now there's no longer
a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to... to, you know, launder it because it
stops being a garment. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דמשייר בה
כדי מעפורת *demashayer bah kedei ma'ofores*. No, you don't completely rend it
in two, you leave at the place of connection enough of a
swath, you know, a thick enough swath, so if you like, you
know, teared it in half, right? So if here's your garment,
so you like tear it in half, okay.
So now whatever, you know, now it's like this, but the thickness
here's enough that it's thick enough down here at the bottom that
you could use that
for like a... for like wrapping some type of a, you know,
like of a lead weight in, like some type of a handkerchief.
Okay, so it's not totally rent in half, there's a thickness at
the bottom that it's thick enough that if you were... that you
know, if you were like cut out that section, you know, you
could use it for something.
So meaning even if it's completely unusable for the function that it
was intended, like if I ripped your shirt down the middle, you
can use it for something else and it's still considered...
Right, the assumption here is that because it's got that and this
itself can be functional if you were to take out that strip,
it has an... it's enough that it loses its initial identity because
it's ripped in half and therefore the טומאה tuma *tumah* goes away,
but if it's enough considered a בגד beged, *beged* that you would
still go be able to go ahead and do this process with
it. But then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks if you're really able
to have this middle state, because maybe if it's enough of a
בגד beged *beged* for this הלכה halacha *halacha* of laundering, it's still
a בגד beged, *beged* for טומאה tuma? *tumah* הלכה halachic *halacha*. So
let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. איני *Eini*, is
this really true? והאמר רב Rav הונא לא שנו אלא שלא שייר
בה כדי מעפורת *Veha'amar Rav Huna lo shanu ela shelo shayer bah
kedei ma'ofores*, but if it's כדי מעפורת *kedei ma'ofores*, when is it
that this rending works in order to make the טומאה tuma *tumah*
go away? Only if you did not leave enough to be used
as like this type of a handkerchief or whatever. אבל שייר בה
כדי מעפורת חיבור הוא *Aval shayer bah kedei ma'ofores chibur hu*, if
you left behind that
much, it's still considered connection and it's still is טמא tamei. *tamei*
because it still is considered to be like, you know, have some
function or something of that nature, it hasn't totally lost its identity.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* answers מדערבנן הוא *miderabbanan hu*. No, that's
only rabbinic, that if you look at רש"י Rashi. *Rashi*, גזירה דילמא
אתו למיקרי רובא *gezeira dilma asu lemikrei ruba*, that biblically if you
tear it at least half, even if, you know, so that's a
lot more than just a little thickness left for a handkerchief. What
I mean, you know, a lot more space left over, but once
you get to half-way tearing it, it's no longer the original garment
and the טומאה tuma *tumah* goes away. And this הלכה halacha *halacha*
that it retains its טומאה tuma *tumah* because if there's a little
left over is rabbinic. Okay, but because biblically it's not טמא tamei.
*tamei*, you're able to bring it into the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash,
*Beis Hamikdash*. But on the other hand, there is this middle space,
that once there's some part of the garment that has not been
fully rendered, on the one hand, if the majority is rendered, it
biblically stops being טמא tamei, *tamei*, rabbinically it is, but we're going
to bracket the rabbinic because here we have to solve this problem.
So biblically it stops being טמא tamei, *tamei*. But because there's still
some part of the garment that's left connected, connected, it's still defined
as a בגד beged, *beged*. Which is a fascinating idea, right? Because
you would say since you didn't put it in a מקוה *mikvah*,
what allows the טומאה tuma *tumah* to go away is that it
stops being a בגד beged, *beged*, right? So
how... what conceptually if you're calling it a בגד beged? *beged*, what
may... the טומאה tuma go away. So one of the things you
could say is well maybe it's a בגד beged but it's not
the original
בגד. beged Okay, and if it's not the original בגד, beged the
טומאה tumah goes away, because the טומאה tumah was contracted with this
as a טלית, talit, it stops being a טלית, talit, you know,
whatever, now it's a handkerchief. Okay, so because it's not the original
thing the טומאה tumah goes away, but because it's still a בגד
beged. you can still laundry. And that to some degree leads to
this big תוספות. Tosafot Okay, but if it still is a בגד,
it's not the original one, why doesn't it get a second degree
of טומאה? tumah Like the טלית talit now touched the handkerchief. When
the טלית talit was in the process of stopping being a טלית
talit and becoming a handkerchief, the handkerchief is also a בגד, just
a different בגד, right? So we understand that the טומאה tumah. goes
away, but why didn't it at least transfer one degree, you know,
derivative to this second type of a בגד? All right, so that's
what that large תוספות Tosafos is about. But the basic answer is
you're able to have a middle state where it's still a בגד
but presumably not the original בגד and therefore you can bring it
in and you can do the laundering. Okay, כלי חרס שיצא, Kli
cheres sheyatza, now we have this pottery one, same type of idea,
you've got to make a hole in it, somehow that stops it
from being a כלי kli to make the טומאה go away, but
it's we'll see it's enough of a כלי kli that you can
do this process of or this מצוה mitzvah of breaking it. So
the גמרא Gemara says כלי אמר רחמנא ולא כלי הוא. kli amar
rachmana velo kli hu. What do you mean? It says that you're
supposed to do a shattering of it as a כלי kli and
it stops being a כלי kli when you make a hole in
it, same question. Okay, you've got to be whole so I can
break you. All right, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says שניקב בשורש
קטן, shenikav beshoresh katan, there's like a little hole in it the
size of a small little root which again is this middle state,
it's enough if it's enough
broken that it stops being like the original כלי kli and by
כלים keilim you have these different degrees of holes for different types
of usages of the כלי kli and so on. So because it's
got a small hole and it can't be used in the original
way, that's enough to make the טומאה go away, but because it's
not totally cracked and you could still use it, you know, you
could use it to hold grapefruits in, you can't use it to
put water in, but you could use it to hold grapefruits, so
therefore it's enough of a כלי kli that you're still doing the
מצוה mitzvah of breaking it. So again this idea that it stops
being the original כלי kli but it's enough of a כלי kli
that you can still go ahead and do this, these מצוות mitzvot
that you're supposed to do with them in, okay, okay,
so now it says like this,
okay, so
כלי נחושת, klei nechoshet, similar question, פוחתו, pocheso, you also make a
opening in it, והלא כלי הוא, vehalo kli hu, it's not a
כלי. kli. So here the גמרא Gemara has a better answer, somewhat
of a better answer, דרציף מרצף. deratzif mirtzaf. Actually here what you
do is actually after you make the hole in it, you're able
you go ahead and רציף ratzif so it says you like, you
like smooth it out, you bang it and you, you know, you
get your hammer, maybe you get your smelting iron and you fix
it afterwards. Okay, so therefore because you fixed it afterwards, it is
a כלי kli now, it stopped being a כלי kli and now
it is a כלי, kli, I mean I guess why you could
have said that by the garment, why don't you go ahead and
you sew it up afterwards or something of that nature, which is
funny because okay, it's a כלי, kli, it's not the original כלי
kli that was cooked in. You could say that if it the
until now the point was was that it didn't fully leave the
status, enough left it for the טומאה to go away, but it
still retained some of its original identity. This answer is actually a
big חידוש, chiddush, because if you say like why didn't the גמרא
Gemara, say I totally tore the garment in half and then I
sewed it back up? So here's a question, if it stops being
a בגד all together, if it stops if it goes from being
a garment to like pieces of cloth and then I resew it
into a garment, is that the מצוה mitzvah of laundering? This isn't
the garment that was there when it's a brand new garment, it's
not the garment that was there when it absorbed the blood, right?
So it was the answer was better when you said no, it
still it still like retains some of its original identity, it hasn't
stopped completely being a בגד. But if this really stopped completely being
a כלי kli and then was refashioned, right, so why is there
still the מצוה mitzvah of scalding it and rinsing it and so
on? You would say that this is something brand new. So I
would prefer the earlier answer, which is is that the hole was,
you know, was big enough to, you know, to what do you
call it, to make it lose some of its original identity but
not to totally lose its original identity. Yes.
There's no idea that the טומאה comes back if you because it's
a new כלי? kli?
Oh yeah, that's דרבנן drabbanan they did that sometimes. You are correct.
But that's not biblical. But you're right, דרבנן drabbanan sometimes they did
that. Okay. So a couple of unanswered questions here about this.
Let's take a look. Now we get on, now we get to
the next state, אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, שמואל, Shmuel,
the מעיל me'il of the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, Michael was asking
that let's say בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna became טמא, tamei, right, and
you have to have a מצוה mitzvah to launder them, are you
able to continue to use them afterwards? Which was that interesting question
of the גמרא, Gemara what degree of staining is so bad that
we would say that after you laundered it it's like not appropriate
to continue using? Anyway, so the גמרא's Gemara not going not going
to relate to that point point of it, but it is going
to deal with the question about the מעיל me'il of the כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, right, this whole long like robe and whatever, and
what happens if that absorbed blood? Okay, so מעיל שנטמא, Me'il shenitma,
so it became so it got blood on it, it was taken...
but he says שנטמא shenitma though,
it doesn't the blood doesn't even...
Yeah but the context is that it became טמא. tamei? Okay, because
of the blood or something? No, no, no, first it got blood
on
it, then it
was taken out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. now it became
It says לא יקרע, lo yikarei, right? It cannot be torn. Okay,
so what are you going to do now? Okay. שנטמא, shenitma, מכניסה
בפחות משלוש על שלוש ומכבסה. machnisa befachos mishalosh al shalosh u'machabsa. You
basically, you're standing right out there, you know, if here's the line
of the עזרה Azarah and here's your מעיל Me'il and you're sticking
in a little piece of the garment at a time, less than
three by three, laundering it, and then like sticking in another little
piece.
Oh, and then you launder each little piece?
Then you launder each little piece until you get the blood out.
Now, the funny part about the thing is,
oh wait, wait, so you actually, you just launder the piece with
the blood on it?
Yeah, that we said before. Yeah, you only have to launder the
spot. You don't have to launder the whole thing. That was the
משנה. Mishnah So anyway, so the חידוש chidush here is, the גמרא'ס
Gemara's question is going to be: שלוש shalosh means שלוש אצבעות, shalosh
etzba'os, okay, that's like a very small piece of cloth is שלוש
אצבעות, shalosh etzba'os, as opposed to שלושה shlosha which is טפחים, tfachim,
which is, you know, much, much bigger. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's question
is going to be what is the minimum size of טומאה for
the מעיל. Me'il. But the bigger question here that I've got is,
if the whole garment is טמא, tamei
you know, then who cares if you're only putting inside the עזרה
Azarah a piece that, had it been cut off, would have been
so small that it would not be טמא. tamei But right now,
it is טמא. tamei It's part of a garment that's טמא, tamei,
and you're putting some of the garment inside the עזרה, Azarah, right?
So the idea of three by three, whether it's whether it's fingers
or טפחים, tfachim, is that if that's the entire size of your
cloth, it's an insignificant cloth and there's no טומאה on it. Okay.
But here there is טומאה on the garment. So it's not a
question of whether the טומאה is there or not. There's a question
about: Do you bring part of the garment in or the whole
garment in? Well, shouldn't that be a problem of ביאה במקצת? bia
bemiktzat? You know, if something is טמא, tamei. like if I'm טמא,
tamei even sticking my finger in would be a problem. So here,
right, we don't say, well, if my finger were cut off, would
it be טמא? tamei No, like I'm טמא and a piece of
me is in. So why isn't that a problem here? So תוספות
Tosafos, asks that question. If you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos
מכניסה בפחות משלוש, machnisa befachos mishalosh, תוספות Tosafot says, אפילו למאן דאמר
בריש כל הפסולים ביאה במקצת שמה ביאה, afillu leman d'amar bereish kol
hapsulim bia bemiktzat shmah bia, that partial entry of something is considered
entry. So so he says, שאני בגד הואיל ויכול לחתכו לא חשיב
כאילו נכנס כולו. shani beged ho'il veyachol lechoch'cho lo chashiv k'illu nichnas
kulo. That actually, no, it is different than if I stick my
finger in. That because a garment you could in theory, people don't,
I mean you could also cut off fingers but thank God people
don't do that so much. Since anyway something is inanimate, you are
able to look at it more as if only... you might remember
before, right, the גמרא Gemara had a whole question about like if
a קרבן korban was on the כבש, kevesh, do you look at
it like it's cut into pieces? Anyway, so here too, you do
look at it. If you only bring in a little piece of
the garment, you conceptually see it as if this piece had been
cut off and was brought in as a tiny little piece. And
since the size is so small that had it been cut off
and brought in only in this tiny size, it would no longer
be טמא because it was such would be such a small size,
therefore you have not violated bringing something טמא in the בית המקדש.
Okay, so when you're dealing with something inanimate and you only stick
in a little piece of it, you look at it as if
that had been cut off and brought in. So that's the גמרא'ס
Gemara's case here. So you so you can't actually cut it, but
you do less than שלוש על שלוש shalosh al shalosh and you
launder it and you're fine. Okay. Put it in outside before you
bring it in? No, there's
no מקוה here. No, but I'm saying is it still טמא, the
garment itself?
Oh, yeah, that's a good point. Yeah. So then you mean how
could the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol ever wear it again because it's
טמא. So I guess it's a good point. After you did that
whole process, you'd have to then put it in the מקוה. Yeah.
It's a good point. Okay. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says, לא יקרע.
lo yikarei. מיתיבי Meisivei רב אדא בר
אהבה, Rav Adda bar Ahava, רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar
Ahava challenged this. העבין והרכין, ha'avin veharachin, garments that are particularly thick
or soft, אין בהם משום שלוש על שלוש. ein bahem mishum shalosh
al shalosh. You they now again there's a whole question what the
גירסא girsa is and how to read this. I'm just going to
read this like רש"י. Rashi They do not go by the size
of three fingers because if they're very thick or very soft, somehow
you don't use them like a normal garment. Three fingers is significant
because you can use it like as a patch. Okay, but if
you've got something like very thick, you're not going to use it
as a patch. So for there to be a significant garment, it's
going to have to be bigger. It's going to be שלושה טפחים
shlosha tfachim by שלושה טפחים. shlosha tfachim. So this is not such
a challenge. It's just like, why did you have to bring it
in in such tiny bits at a time, שלוש על שלוש shalosh
al shalosh finger-widths? Since your מעיל Me'il is a very thick garment,
you should be allowed you know, you should be allowed
to bring in larger sections at a time?
Or maybe something the opposite, smaller, no?
No, the way רש"י Rashi is reading it is that this is
a thick garment. So therefore you should have been allowed to bring
in a larger section at a time because thick garments you don't
use as patches and only larger sections are significant. So גמרא Gemara
says, אגב אביהן חשיבי. agav avihen chashivi.
You're right, had it really been cut out, שלוש shalosh three fingers
by three fingers would not be enough to be a problem. But
because it is attached to the original מעיל Me'il and the original
מעיל Me'il is obviously... is significant. So then even three finger widths
of it is significant. So it's a very bizarre point. Right, you're
able to bring in a small amount, and the reason that's not
considered violating bringing something טמא is you envision it as if it
had been cut off. And you said had this been cut off,
it would be so small that it would not retain טומאה. And
therefore it's okay to stick a little piece of it in. But,
you don't get to say, had this been cut off and used
the three טפחים tfachim by three טפחים. tfachim. Since it's still at
the end of the day is connected, you have to use the
smaller measure and only go by the tiniest amount that normally we
allow for garments, which is under three fingers by three fingers. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara? has another question. והבעי שבעה סממנים. Ve-ha-bai
shiva simmanim. One minute, says the גמרא, Gemara. how can you ever
the way רש"י Rashi reads it, I'll tell you how תוספות Tosafot
reads it in a minute, but the way רש"י Rashi reads it
is
how do you ever do the laundering, because we've never discussed how
do you launder the garments, the blood, what do you do? Do
you soak, what do you do? So Michael correctly remembers that there's
a teaching that the way you sort of launder, whether it's about
getting out bloodstains for נידה niddah הלכות halakhot or whether it's about
צרעת tzaraat or whether it's about this type of a blood, you
use seven different types of what do you call it of cleansing
agents and we're going to see in a minute you have to
do it in a particular order and rub with each one and
so on. Well, one of those cleanse so presumably we're now assuming
that that is the way in which you do this מצוה of
laundering the blood that the Torah says. Well, the problem is one
of those cleansing agents is urine and you're not allowed to bring
urine into the
עזרה. Azarah. So now this is really a question has nothing to
do with our מעיל. me'il. You could just have asked on the
משנה. Mishna And רש"י Rashi says to a certain degree we are
asking it or you know on the משנה mishna, or you also
ask in general how do you do this cleansing. But it doesn't
sound that way from context. So תוספות Tosafot says that the reason
we're asking it here is is because that
one minute.
Yes, because really there's another alternative to using these seven agents. There's
a type of an agent that you could use called צפון tzafon
or צפון tzafun I guess I don't know anyway sort of like
a type of a bleach, okay, and that will also get out
the stain and you could normally use that bleach. There's only a
reason why you can't use the bleach on the מעיל. me'il. Why
can't you use the bleach on the מעיל? me'il?
The מעיל me'il would be getting out the color.
Because you'll be getting out the color. So that's what תוספות Tosafot
says. Normally we don't have to use the urine. That's the nice
delicate way that gets out the stain and that retains the color
whatever. Normally we'd just use bleach, okay. And that's how so it's
fascinating by the way that this הלכה halacha of תכבס במקום קדוש
techabes bimkom kadosh like you know that the חז"ל Chazal didn't ritualize
it more. They really just said you know the way תוספות Tosafot
reads it like use whatever cleansing agent is going to get it
out. Okay. So normally fine we'll use bleach not a problem. Ah,
but by the מעיל me'il we can't use bleach, it'll get out
the color. So you can use something else? So presumably they thought
the only alternative was these seven cleansing agents which included urine and
now what are we going to do? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara.
says, והבעי שבעה סממנים, Ve-ha-bai shiva simmanim, but doesn't it require the
seven cleansing agents? דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה De-amar Rav
Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha דם חטאת, dam chatat, the blood of
a חטאת, chatat, and here he explicitly says that this seven cleansing
agents is to apply to the blood of a חטאת, chatat, ומראות
נגעים u-marot nega'im צריכים שבעה סממנים. tsrichim shiva simmanim. It requires the
seven agents. Okay. ותניא Ve-tanya אלו שאין מכניסין מי רגלים למקדש eilu
she-ein machnisin mei raglayim la-mikdash by the you know by the issue
that Michael says, by the קטורת ketoret urine would have made it
smell better but you're not allowed to bring it in. Okay. וכי
תימא Ve-chi teima now lest you say, דמבלע להו בהני שבעה סממנים.
de-mivla lehu be-hanei shiva simmanim. Okay, you know you don't bring in
the urine by itself but you can mix it up with the
other agents. Of course you want to mix it up also with
the with the קטורת ketoret maybe because you have to you'd have
to bring it in to mix it with the קטורת ketoret you
don't bring the קטורת ketoret out. But here maybe why don't you
mix up all the cleansing agents outside the עזרה Azarah and bring
them in in a nice mixture? So the גמרא Gemara, says ומהוו
להו לכולהו כחד u-mavu lehu lekulu ke-achad and you use them all
as one? No, that won't be effective. והתנן Ve-hatnan העבירן שלא כסדרן
או שהעביר שבעתן כאחת ha-aviran she-lo ke-sidran o she-ha-avir shivatan ke-echad לא
עשה ולא כלום. lo asa velo klum. If you use them out
of order or you mixed them all together you know it's like
when you're what do you call it when your washing detergent contains
bleach right? So sometimes you get a feeling like is that going
to be as good as if I actually use the bleach separately
and then... anyway so if you mix it all together it won't
be effective. So you can't so you still got the problem right?
You can't you know what do you do with the urine? You
can't mix it together and you can't have it separ... you know
mixing it together will lose its effectiveness and separate will be a
problem. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא דמבלע להו בהדי חד
מסממנים. ve-chi teima de-mivla lehu be-hadai chad mi-simmanim. So one minute maybe
the point is that you mix it just together with one. Maybe
the problem is don't mix all seven together but maybe if you
mix it with one of them you know that'll be effective. וצריך
לכסכס. Ve-tzarich le-chaskhes. Remember we did כסכוס kiskus the other day right?
Which is like the vigorous rubbing of the parts of the of
the garment. together לכסכס שלש פעמים בכל אחד ואחד, Lachas'ches shalosh pe'amim
bechol echad ve'echad, no, so it's not. But the משנה says that
each one has to be separate and with each application of each
of the סמנין sammanim you have to do a separate rubbing, and
that's how it's gonna be effective. So we got the problem, urine
has to be used separately. How you gonna make, how you gonna
do this? You can't bring urine into the עזרה. Azarah. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא דמבלעי להו ברוק תפל, Ella demavlei lehu berok
tafel, fine, add some spit. And that's considered acceptable? That's acceptable, that's
not to mix it with one of the other seven agents would
actually lose its effectiveness, either it would lose effectiveness or the other
agent would lose its effectiveness. But to have it by itself and
to add a little spit into it, it doesn't lose its effectiveness
and that makes it not enough straight urine that it would be
an offense. Right, so just add a little bit of spit so
or makes that not enough? I don't know, yeah, you think maybe
it would need to be a רוב rov spit or something, I
don't know. דאמר ריש לקיש רוק תפל צריך שיהא כל אחד ואחד.
De'amar Reish Lakish, rok tafel tzarich shehei kol echad ve'echad. Ah, because
anyway, by the way, this isn't even just a סתם stam thing
we're doing to get rid of the urine problem, it actually would
be the normal way we would do it. We would add a
little spit with each one. So somehow by adding a little spit
with each one, which would be normal way we would do it,
that would make it acceptable to bring in the urine. It is
a little funny, like urine with a little spit is all of
a sudden acceptable. Anyway, that's the cleansing. And it makes it even
more potent. I understand. Now we move on from the cleansing. Rambam
disagrees. Rambam disagrees with what? With the גמרא? Gemara Using the urine.
What? Rambam disagrees with using the urine. So what do you do?
He says all the detergents are used except for the urine. Interesting.
Alright, have to look into that. Alright, so they give you the
stuff. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, fine, very nice. Alright, now we move
on from the garment to the to the cooking. Okay? So, it's
very, very appropriate for the Nine Days, right? You're not supposed to
do laundry, you're not supposed to cook meat. So we move from
doing laundry to cooking meat. Okay, fine. So here we go. You
can cook meat, I guess, you can't eat it. Alright, anyway, let's
take a look. אחד שבישל בו, Echad shebishal bo, so now we
just glide without even an introduction that we're now about to shift
gears and go from the blood on the חטאת chatat to a
cooking of a חטאת, chatat, we're just assuming now we're talking about
the cooking of a חטאת chatat where the תורה Torah says that
if it's in a pottery you just shatter it, and then if
it's in a metal vessel again you do the scalding and the
rinsing. Okay? So אחד שבישל בו ואחד שעירה לתוכו רותח, Echad shebishal
bo ve'echad she'irah letocho roteach, whether you actually cooked in this pot,
put it directly over the fire with the חטאת chatat or we'll
see other קרבנות korbanot in a minute, or whether you cooked in
a different pot and poured into this pot. Okay, that's enough. So
that's a big חידוש, chiddush, which I'll discuss in a minute. ואחד
קדשי קדשים ואחד קדשים קלים טעונים מריקה ושטיפה, Ve'echad kodshei kodashim ve'echad
kodashim kalim te'unim merika ushtifa, whether it is not only a חטאת,
chatat, it's even the קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, an עולה, olah, an
אשם, asham, and not even that, even קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, even
a שלמים. shelamim. רבי אליעזר אומר קדשים קלים אין טעונים מריקה ושטיפה.
Rabbi Eliezer omer kodashim kalim ein te'unim merika ushtifa. No, it doesn't
apply to קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, it only applies to קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. So we mentioned that earlier, we'll see about that in
the גמרא. Gemara But before we get to which types of קרבנות,
korbanot, we're gonna focus on this idea of אשר תבושל בו, asher
tevushal bo, cooking, and whether it includes also pouring. Okay? And big
תוספות Tosafot in because there's just a lot of other הלכה halachah?
implications for these issues. So let's take a look. Wait, Rabbi Shimon.
Yeah, I have Rabbi Shimon. What did I say? Rabbi Eliezer? I'm
sorry, I have Rabbi Shimon also, I don't know why I said
Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, רבי שמעון אומר קדשים קלים אין טעונים מריקה ושטיפה,
Rabbi Shimon omer kodashim kalim ein te'unim merika ushtifa, fine. Okay. גמרא.
gemara תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: אשר תבושל בו. Asher tevushal bo. אין
לי אלא שבישל בו, Ein li ella shebishal bo, it says that
you cooked in it. עירה לתוכו רותח מניין? Ira letocho roteach minayin?
How do you know if you just poured boiling hot water, like
a stew, חטאת chatat stew into a pot that the pot that
received it also has to be go through this process? תלמוד לומר
ואשר תבושל בו. Talmud lomar va'asher tevushal bo. So our גירסא girsa
is ואשר, va'asher, and that. רש"י Rashi, actually says that the גירסא
girsa is בו ישבר, bo yishaver, even if it was just in
it, even if it wasn't cooked in it, like bracketing the word
תבושל. tevushal. Okay, but obviously not just סתם stam in it, סתם
stam in it poured in hot. And this by the way, I
should say, there's this long תוספות tosafos you see עירה לתוכו, ira
letocho, because this is a classic debate of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
and the רשב"ם Rashbam in many areas of the גמרא, gemara which
is what is the halachic status of עירוי? irui? Of pouring something
hot? Does pouring something hot cook something? So you can imagine a
couple of scenarios. Let's talk about a שבת Shabbos scenario. I have
my tea bag and I pour boiling hot water onto my tea
bag. Have I just now transgressed cooking on שבת? Shabbos? We normally
say that cooking requires a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, requires something to
be directly on the fire, okay, or in the same vessel that
was on the fire, okay? So there I am, I'm cooking my
chicken soup on the fire or even let's say I move the
pot off the fire but it was the one that had been
on the fire and I throw in some stuff into it, right?
So that could be a problem of בישול. bishul. I throw in
some raw onions into it or something like that. Okay? When I
go ahead and take it from that pot and now I turn
move turn it pour it into a tureen and now I've got
that tureen is a כלי שני. kli sheni. So now if I
put stuff in the tureen, the general assumption is that a כלי
שני kli sheni is not מבשל. mevashal. A כלי שני kli sheni
doesn't cook. Okay?
There's a whole debates about קלי הבישול kallei habishul since they cook
easily but fine. So we know...
כלי ראשון kli rishon cooks and a כלי שני kli sheni doesn't
cook. What about the space between a כלי ראשון kli rishon and
a כלי שני? kli sheni? When I am pouring from the pot
into the tureen and there's some of these raw onions at the
bottom of the pot of the tureen and it hits it or
like when I'm pouring from the kettle onto the tea bag, it's
going from the כלי ראשון kli rishon into the כלי שני. kli
sheni. The water that's coming down is connected to the כלי ראשון,
kli rishon, but the thing that the water is hitting, right, is
not being cooked in the כלי ראשון, kli rishon, it is in
a new כלי. kli. Is that is עירוי iruy of a כלי
ראשון, kli rishon, is it בישול bishul or not בישול? bishul? So
this is a major debate. The two major obvious areas that this
would be a question would
be שבת Shabbos and where else does בישול bishul matter? Can you
think? Would there be a big deal about whether something's considered בישול
bishul or not?
בישול עכו"ם? bishul akum? Well בישול עכו"ם's bishul akum a good question,
that's true, although that has its interesting ones parameters. בשר בחלב. basar
bechalav. Right, let's say I did that and I poured some boiling
hot milk onto some beef. Have I transgressed the biblical violation of
cooking meat and milk together? Now, there's also a question about, which
is a little different than בישול, bishul, is a question of בליעה.
bliah. Does something absorb? Because you could say, you know what, for
שבת Shabbos it's not a problem, cooking means cooking on the fire
or on something that was on the fire. You don't cook by
pouring hot water off things or certainly not a normal way of
cooking. But if I want to know if I have some חזיר
chazir soup and I'm pouring it into my tureen, it might not
be that it's not cooking anything in my tureen, but it's still
hot enough and coming from something that had been directly on the
fire whatever that it's getting now absorbed into the walls of my
tureen. That's called בליעה, bliah, that's called absorption, which is not the
same as an act of cooking. So this is a major debate
of the רשב"א Rashba and רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. Does עירוי iruy
cook or not cook? And obviously there are three positions. I don't
know obviously. One is it doesn't cook, the other is it does
cook, and the third position is it cooks a little bit. It
cooks כדי קליפה, kedei klipa, like at the surface level it cooks.
Now, if you were to pour boiling
hot water onto something, like the first like the very sort of
exterior so
if you had a piece of meat and
you poured boiling hot milk on
it, the exterior surface of the meat would be considered בשר בחלב
basar bechalav but the inner part not because you can also understand
that, right, because it hits the surface it doesn't get fully absorbed
if it's not immersed in the thing it's just the thing is
being hit in it. The very interesting הלכה halacha?
application of this, which was a regular application in the time of
the ראשונים rishonim for us less so, is that you have your
chicken here and I've just slaughtered
my chicken and I want to now pluck the feathers.
So the easy way to pluck the feathers is you pour scalding
hot water on it, somehow that loosens it up and makes it
easy to pluck the feathers. The problem would be that when the
scalding hot water hits it, the chicken has not yet been salted
and the blood is still in it. And the הלכה halacha, is
that when you cook something then the blood will go out and
come back in because cooking basically makes stuff mix up, it doesn't
sort of stuff that cooks sort of traces are moving in and
out. So therefore if that's considered cooking, now the depending on how
much it cooked, the whole chicken or the outer layer of the
chicken or whatever, now you can't remove the blood from the chicken
because it's cooked the chicken in its own blood. All right, anyway
so that was a whole question and the the sort of the
resolution was well maybe it's true about the outer skin and the
outer layer maybe not the inner part and so on. Anyway so
this is a major major debate about what is the status of
עירוי iruy of pouring from a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, is it
like cooking or not? So our conclusion of our גמרא gemara says
even if you do עירוי iruy to some degree part of the
question is how does the גמרא gemara's learn it out? So רש"י,
Rashi if I as I mentioned, takes out the word תבשל. tivashal.
רש"י Rashi says the גמרא's Gemara question is עירוי לתוכו מנין תלמוד
לומר אשר בו תשבר. iruy letocho minayin talmud lomar asher bo tishaver.
So רש"י Rashi, sort of understands and we're going to see not
only רש"י, the גמרא Gemara in a minute is going to actually
say that עירוי iruy tells you you don't need בישול, bishul, even
if it just was poured in and it got absorbed into the
pot, even without being cooked in the pot, nevertheless it is still
the הלכה halacha still applies. So this seems to conclude that עירוי
iruy is not considered בישול. bishul. And let's continue with that in
a minute and you'll see that in a minute and then I'll
go back and say how the other position would explain this. בעי
רמי בר חמא. baei Rami bar Chama. So that's the answer even
if you just did עירוי iruy even if you didn't do בישול
bishul it is still going to be a problem and you're still
going to need, I mean that's our משנה, ואחד שעירו לתוכו, ve'echad
she'iro letocho, you're still going to need to do this מריקה ושפיפה.
merika ushfifa. So בעי רמי בר חמא. baei Rami bar Chama. רמי
בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked, תלאו באויר תנור מה? talao be'avir
tanur mah? Let's say you went ahead and now the vessel here
we're talking about is the oven, an oven is a type of
a vessel, it's considered to be whatever movable. So you went ahead
and you have here, here's your oven which is your כלי, kli,
okay, and here's your spit roasting your חטאת chatas in your oven,
okay, and here's the fire. So what is the story? Does the
oven require like מריקה ושטיפה merikah u'shtifah or if it's a כלי
חרס kli cheres שבירה? shvirah? So the חטאת chatas was cooked in
the oven. It is אשר תבושל בו asher tivushal bo because it
was cooked in it. But, and this gets to a whole question
about, you know, ovens and steam and is it a problem using
a non-kosher oven if, you know, because nothing is actually touching the
walls of the oven, it's just transferred by the steam. So the
assumption is the חטאת chatas is cooked in the oven, but it's
not absorbed into the, the taste isn't absorbed into the walls of
the oven. So this is considered something that has בשול, bishul, check,
it was cooked, but it has no בליעה, blee'ah, it was not
absorbed into the walls. Okay, and we're assuming that the case of
ערוי irui is the opposite. The case of ערוי, irui, right, which
is here, here, okay, this is the thing that had been cooked
in, this is the thing that had been on the fire, okay,
and you're now pouring into it from, you know, your חטאת chatas
stew into this, that was the case of ערוי. irui. So it
wasn't cooked in here, right? So this case of ערוי, irui, we're
saying בשול, bishul, אשר תבושל, asher tivushal, no, but it is absorbed,
בליעה, blee'ah, yes. That was our case of ערוי. irui. So, okay,
got it? So we said in this case, you've got to go
ahead and do the pro and do the מריקה ושטיפה, merikah u'shtifah,
do the breaking. What about this case which is the mirror image?
It's got בשול bishul but it doesn't have absorption. This is absorption
without having a בשול. bishul. So the גמרא Gemara. says like this:
In the cases where the חטאת chatas was טמא or is this
just... no, no, no, any normal case of a חטאת chatas that
you have because the tastes get absorbed and then it becomes נותר
nosar and all those types of things. So any time you do...
any time you cook a חטאת, chatas, you're going to have to
do this. So, like, I don't know what person is actually using
pottery vessels because then you're going to be breaking them on a
daily basis. The point would be use metal vessels and then but
you do have to kosher them regularly. Yeah, but pottery vessels every
time you cook the חטאת. chatas. Yeah, because of נותר. nosar. Because,
yeah, I mean, really because it's a פסוק, pasuk, but the conceptual
explanation of the פסוק pasuk is that it absorbs the taste and
then it becomes נותר nosar and so on. Okay, so anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, תלאו באויר תנור מהו. tala'o
b'avir tannur mahu. What's the הלכה? halacha אבשול ובליעה הוא דקפיד רחמנא?
a'bishul u'vlee'ah hu d'kapid rachmana? Do you need both cooking and absorbing?
או דילמא בשול בלא בליעה? o dilma bishul belo blee'ah? Or maybe
cooking even without absorbing? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, רבא Rava says,
תא שמע אחד שבישל בו ואחד שעירה לתוכו רותח. Ta shema, echad
shebishil bo ve'echad she'eirah letocho rotei'ach. Learn it out from our case
we just did about pouring in the boiling hot stuff. So that
shows you that one is sufficient. So the answer is no, בליעה
בלא בשול לא קמיבעי לן. blee'ah belo bishul lo kamibaya lan. Yes,
yes, I know that absorbing suffices by itself. You're right. From here
we see that absorbing by itself is sufficient. What I want to
know is the mirror image when you have just the בשול bishul
and not the absorption. Okay, לא קמיבעי לן, lo kamibaya lan, כי
קמיבעי לן, ki kamibaya lan, what's my question? בשול בלא בליעה, bishul
belo blee'ah, cooking without absorbing, is that sufficient? So מאי, mai, what's
the story? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דאמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה תנור של מקדש של מתכת היה. d'amar Rav
Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha tannur shel mikdash shel mateches hayah. They
would use a metal oven. Okay, for exactly this reason. Who wants
to be making a new oven every day? Okay, ואי סלקא דעתך
בשול בלא בליעה לא קפיד, ve'ee salka dach'tach bishul belo blee'ah lo
kapid, and if you're right that cooking without absorbing didn't matter, so
why did they need to make it metal, right? So לא קפיד,
נעביד של חרס, lo kapid na'avid shel cheres. make it pottery. And
again, the assumption would be that you would not put, you might
put something in there in a pot, you might put it in
a spit, but it wasn't going to directly touch the pottery. And
if it wasn't going to touch the pottery, what's the issue? So
you see that absorbing doesn't matter. You see that בשול bishul alone
suffices to be this issue. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קפיד
lo kapid, נעביד של חרס. na'avid shel cheres, No, the גמרא's Gemara
answer is כיון דאיכא שירי מנחות דאפייתן בתנור. keivan d'ika sheirei menachos
d'afiyasum betannur. No, no, no, there are things that actually do directly
touch the oven. What touches the oven? When you actually bake bread
in it. Okay, so if you're baking the remnant of the מנחה
minchah and you're putting it in the oven to make it into
a nice, you know, because it had a nicer type of a
thing after the מנחה minchah was brought, that is getting absorbed, okay?
And this isn't just limited to a חטאת, chatas, you'll remember. Okay,
ואיכא בשול ובליעה. ve'ika bishul u'vlee'ah. In that case it has both
בשול bishul and בליעה. blee'ah. עבדינן של מתכת, avdinan shel mateches, we
make it of metal. So you can't prove from the fact that
they wanted a metal oven that בשול bishul without בליעה blee'ah wasn't...
Because there were some things they would have used the oven for
that would have had בלוע viloa as well. So in the end
of the day we don't have our answer. What is the story
here with just בישול bishul without בלוע, viloa, would this require this
הלכה? halacha Now I want to make a couple points. First should
be the obvious one, which is a very important point which is,
hello, does everybody realize that what the גמרא Gemara basically just said
is is that we don't have to worry about absorption by ovens
if it's not directly touching the wall of the oven, right? So
all of our issues about like you know using kosher ovens or
whatever, I mean I'm not talking talking about cooking טרפה traife and
kosher stuff in the same oven at the same time, but I'm
talking about sequential, the simple reading of the גמרא Gemara is is
that there's really no problem. And there are definitely you know significant
significant halachic positions that basically say that if there's no ממשות mamashus
like if there's no like חזיר chazer grease on the base of
an oven or whatever, that you know what I'm saying, if it's
like physically clean and it's just a question of what got absorbed
into the walls that if nothing was physically touching whatever it's not
a problem and you don't have to worry about the question of
kosher ovens or whatever if it's your you know if you don't
have a טרפה traife thing in it at the same time. That
is certainly the simple sense of this גמרא. Gemara. I want to
actually now make another point though about the גמרא Gemara. seems to
have decided on this debate of רשב"ם Rashbam and רבינו תם. Rabbeinu
Tam. The גמרא Gemara seems to be very clear that this isn't
בישול, bishul, that this is just בליעה, bliah, right, it said explicitly,
absorbing without בישול. bishul. So how could anybody say that pouring עירוי
כלי ראשון irui k'li rishon is בישול bishul if this גמרא Gemara
says it's just בליעה? bliah? So do you want to know what
the answer is? The גמרא Gemara says explicitly this is absorbing without
cooking, and I told you that there's a major debate whether pouring
scalding hot stuff is considered cooking or not. So the answer is,
if you pour scalding hot stuff, let's say you've got your tea
here. You might be cooking the tea, that might be true. But
you're not cooking, the cooking wasn't sort of done in it. Since
the fire wasn't here, right, the cooking was done sort of from
the water that was coming elsewhere. But it's still not that it
was cooked within, I mean it sort of was cooked within in
like it was cooked in its space. But it wasn't sort of
the thing that did the cooking, okay? And therefore, that's a way
of explaining that the water coming in might cook something here, but
it's still true to say that the cooking wasn't done with the
vessel. The vessel wasn't the instrument of cooking, okay? So anyway, that's
this debate of whether this actually achieves cooking of the object down
here, but the simple reading of the גמרא Gemara is that it
does not. That this is absorbing without cooking, cooking is only in
the כלי ראשון, k'li rishon, not in stuff that's being poured onto
it, that's at least the simple reading of the גמרא. Gemara And
this scenario would be cooking without absorbing. Okay, so you can see
these are all very relevant to other areas of הלכה, halacha okay,
whether it's about ovens, whether it's about עירוי, irui, whatever the case
might be. So now let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. ההוא תנורא, Hahu tanura, there
was an oven, דאטו ביה טיחיא, d'atu bei tichya, that was smeared
with some type of a like fat, okay, some animal fat. אסר
רבה בר אשי, Assar Rabba bar Ashi, kosher animal fat, למיכליה ריפתא
לעולם. l'michlei rifta l'olam. He said you could never use this oven
for baking bread. Everything you make in this oven will always be
פליישיק fleishig and because it'll always be פליישיק fleishig you can't use
it for bread. Why? Because there's a הלכה halacha that חז"ל chazal
did not allow מילכיק milchig bread or פליישיק fleishig bread, because since
bread was a staple, they figured that you know don't say oh
I have מילכיק milchig bread I'll just eat it with my מילכיקס.
milchigs. No. Because it's a staple, anything that's bread you'll come to
eat with everything else, okay? So there since so therefore since this
oven will always be פליישיק, fleishig, any bread here is אסור assur
לעולם. l'olam. ואפילו במלחא, V'afilu b'milcha, even just with salt, even if
you're going to meaning even if you're not going to eat it
with anything else. דילמא אתי למיכליה בכותחא Dilma asi l'michlei b'kucha because
if you've got bread and it's פליישיק fleishig bread, we're not going
to let you eat it because you might eat it with כותחא
kucha and the same is true about מילכיק milchig bread, which raises
a problem because there definitely are a lot of bread products that
are מילכיק. milchig. So the basic there's debates about when what is
the scope of this prohibition. If the bread is something that is
I wouldn't be called bread, it's more like a muffin, or it's
more like a whatever, that's not a problem. If it's a type
of a thing that it's ניכר, nikar, it's obvious by the way
it's shaped or by how it looks that it's not normal bread,
that it might be a מילכיק milchig type of a bread, you
know, other types of issues. The big question is is it enough
that you put like a little סימן siman on it after you
cook it. So can I go ahead and have מילכיק milchig bread
if the packaging has an OUD? Actually considering that OUD we all
know doesn't half the time doesn't mean dairy that might not be
enough, but okay. But anyway but that's anyway that's an interesting questions
about this, but anyway that's the basic point. So basic point is
this stuff is always going to remain פליישיק fleishig and therefore the
bread is always going to be a problem. Is there no ביטול
bitul here, the ביטול בששים bitul b'shishim or something? Right, the assumption
is, yeah, the I mean the assumption is that enough of it
got in, I mean you'd have to figure out the proportion. Yeah,
normally we don't say that. I mean I hear your point. Like
you're right, normally we say we go by the amount that was
absorbed in and we don't sort of just say like well let's
distribute it over how many times the thing was used etc. Yeah
we normally don't do that type of stuff. So מיתיבי Meitivei I'll
ask you on this that you say it's always a problem. We
have a ברייתא braita that says the following. אין לשין את העיסה
בחלב, Ein lashin et ha'isa b'chalav, you don't go, this is now
the problem of milkic bread. Don't go ahead and knead dough with
milk. ואם לש כל הפת כולה אסורה, V'im lash kol hapat kula
asura, and if so it's all, it's forbidden, okay, even with, you
know, eat with milkics. ומפני הרגל עבירה, Umipnei hergel aveira, because it'll
lead to doing an עבירה, aveira, because, you know, you'll eat your
bread with everything. כיוצא בו, Keyotzei bo, similarly, אין טשין את התנור
באליה, ein tashin et hatanur b'alya, exactly our case. Don't use a
fat tail to smear the oven, okay? ואם טש כל הפת כולה
אסורה, V'im tash kol hapat kula asura, and if so the bread
is פליישג fleishig and it's forbidden. And here's so far it's completely
consistent. Here's the contradiction: עד שיסיק את התנור, ad sheyasik et hatanur,
until you burn out the oven, okay? So you can כשר kasher
an oven by burning it out, and you said it always remains
טרייף. treif. Okay, so you see there's a way of כשר kashering
an oven, even a pottery oven, presumably that's what we're talking about,
by lighting the fire, you know what we say for people that
are doing it for פסח, Pesach, like turn it on self-clean, wait
an hour, blah, blah, blah. Here you have it, right? Turn on
the fire, let the fire burn it all out. So you see
there's a way of כשר kashering it. So the גמרא Gemara says
תיובתא דרבא בר אילעי תיובתא. Tyufta d'Rava bar Ilai tyufta. That is
a contradiction. You see there is a way of כשר kashering an
oven. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to say, oh wait,
so there's a way to כשר kasher pottery things? So nobody ever
told me that. Why isn't this a solution for anytime, you know,
the type of pottery things absorb? You're always telling me there's no
way to כשר kasher it. You gotta break it, throw it out
or whatever. You just told me now here there's a way to
כשר. kasher. Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא says
like this. So אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי. Amar lei Ravina l'Rav
Ashi. So רבינא said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ומאחר דאיסתתר רבא
בר אילעי, u'meachar d'istatar Rava bar Ilai, now that רבא בר אילעי
Rava bar Ilai was contradicted and you told me that by putting
something into the fire you can כשר kasher it, even pottery, אמאי
אמר רב קדרות בפסח ישברו? amai amar Rav kederot b'Pesach yishaveru? Why
does he say that, you know, if you have a, that if
you have a חמץ chametz vessel, and meaning a קדירה kedera like
it's a pot, meaning a pottery thing, you have to break it,
meaning that there is no way to כשר? kasher? So why can't
you just כשר, kasher, why can't you just put it go ahead
in in back into the oven and burn it out? So אמר
ליה רב מוקי לה לההיא בשל מתכת, Amar lei Rav moki lah
l'hahi b'shel matechet, which, no, רב said when did we talk about
burning out an oven that you could כשר kasher it? By metal.
Pottery you can't כשר, kasher, which now by the way come and
defend the argument about the about the oven. When he said that
it was always going to be פליישג, fleishig, maybe he meant pottery.
So now we've taken a step back. Actually, forget what we just
said. Okay, if it's pottery, you can't כשר, kasher, you can't burn
it out. When we said that you could burn out an oven
and כשר kasher it, we only meant metal. But now the גמרא
is going to concede, no, no, no, we did mean pottery. Okay,
ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, if you want I'll tell you, בתנור של
חרס, b'tanur shel cheres, you are right. Okay, fine, it is what
we said before. Even a pottery oven you can כשר. kasher. But
here's the difference. There's a difference between an oven and a pot.
זה היסיקו מבפנים וזה היסיקו מבחוץ. Ze hiseiko mibifnim v'ze hiseiko mibachutz.
When you כשר kasher an oven, you put the fire inside the
oven itself, okay? So yes, can you כשר kasher pottery by putting
it into a fire? If the fire is in the pottery, it'll
כשר kasher the pottery. That'll be intense enough and so on to
כשר kasher the pottery. If you take a pot, a pottery pot
that's been טרייף treif or that's חמץ chametz or whatever, and you
put it into an oven, it won't כשר kasher it because the
fire surrounds it, but the fire isn't in the pot itself. So
now we are saying here is a way to כשר. kasher. Pottery
ovens can be כשר kashered if the fire's inside, but pots can't
be כשר kashered because the fire's outside. So the גמרא says one
minute. So the גמרא says, ונעביד היסיקו מבפנים? V'na'avid hiseiko mibifnim? Fine,
I'll just put a fire inside of my pot. I'll take my
pottery pot and I'll put some coals in it. Still let me
כשר kasher it. So the answer is, חייס עלייהו דלמא פקעי. Chayas
aleihu dilma pak'ei. No, because you'll be afraid, you won't do it
as hot enough or as big enough as it requires, you're afraid
it'll ruin it. So technically speaking, you're right. If you would put
a big enough fire inside of your pot, pottery pot, you could
כשר kasher it. But we're not going to allow that as a
form of כשר. kashering. We'll allow it for ovens, but we're not
going to allow it for pottery because you're going to try to
protect it. So the גמרא says הילכך, Hilkach, and therefore, האי כובייא,
hai kuvya, this type of a כובייא, kuvya, which is a type
of like a sort of like a pot-like type of a thing,
היסיקו מבחוץ הוא, hiseiko mibachutz hu, so again you put the fire
around it, you don't actually put the fire in it, ואסור, v'asur,
and it's אסור. asur. Okay, fine. So that's the answer. Pottery ovens
you can כשר kasher because the fire's inside, but pottery pots you
can't כשר. kasher. Okay, now. The גמרא has the next question. By
the way, I do need to pause and say that there is
a question about the whole issue before about the פליישג fleishig oven.
And the question about the פליישג fleishig oven... is, you might be
aware that there is a principle called נט בר נט, nat bar
nat, which is נותן טעם בר נותן טעם, nosein ta'am bar nosein
ta'am, two degrees removed of taste, if we're dealing not with something
that's טרייף, treif, but just מילכיגס milchigs or פליישיגס, fleishigs, stops being
a problem. So for example, I mean, if I go ahead and
I cook my noodles in a פליישיג fleishig pot. Because the פליישיגס
fleishigs are two degrees removed, and פליישיגס fleishigs is only פליישיגס, fleishigs,
it's not טרייף. treif. So first the פליישיגס, fleishigs, the chicken soup
went into the pot. Then it went from the pot into the
noodles. Okay, the הלכה is that those noodles are actually פרווע. pareve.
All right. Now, there's some, I don't, don't go ahead and say
that as an על מעשה al-maiseh הלכה because actually the actual הלכה
is is that לכתחילה l'chatchila we don't mix those noodles with butter,
but בדיעבד b'dieved if you did mix it with butter it's okay
and so on etc. etc. Anyway, but at least the simple understanding
is that's פרווע. pareve. תוספות tosafos says, so I don't understand the
problem with this פליישיג fleishig bread. It's just like the noodles in
my פליישיג fleishig pot. The, right? It's נט בר נט, nat bar
nat, it's two degrees removed. Why is the bread פליישיג? fleishig? All
right? So one answer is, ah, maybe actually the noodles aren't, are
a problem. Okay, maybe it's not so simple, two degrees removed. Maybe
it depends and that's the whole question about what makes something two
degrees removed. Maybe if it's directly over a fire it doesn't go
down a degree, etc. etc. But תוספות's other answer to that question,
and that's why the הלכה is don't לכתחילה l'chatchila put put butter
on the noodles, okay, because it is a little bit of a
question whether it's considered two degrees removed, okay, and partly you see
that by this oven. Okay. The other answer though is that the
oven has all those nooks and crannies in the walls of it,
it's pottery. So the stuff doesn't really totally just remain, get in
the walls and go away, even the actual, you know, פליישיגס fleishigs
itself, a film of it still remains on the surface of the
oven. You got it? Because the, you know, you imagine right that
it's pottery or whatever. So anyway, I just, I just wanted to
point out that little interesting parenthetical point, which is why is this
oven such a problem? Isn't it the standard principle of נט בר
נט nat bar nat from the פליישיגס fleishigs to the oven, from
the oven to the bread? And the answer to that is one
of two. Either you know what, you're right. נט בר נט nat
bar nat is not so obvious. Maybe there are cases where נט
בר נט nat bar nat is a problem. Okay. And the other
possibility is no, it's because it's an oven and it's pottery and
therefore the, the actual פליישיגס fleishigs get remains on the surface, remains
on the wall etc. Okay, so right now what we've said is
you actually can כשר kasher pottery oven because the fire's on the
inside and in theory you could כשר kasher pottery pots if you
put the fire on the inside but we don't exactly trust you.
Okay. We will pick up tomorrow with the question of so why
do you have to destroy the pots of the חטאת chatas in
the תורה? Torah? Why can't you just also כשר kasher them? Okay.
So we will, why do you have to break them? Because now
you're actually telling me is that at least in theory there's a
way to כשר kasher pottery. All right. So we'll pick up with
that question tomorrow.